[Music]
w
good evening good day everybody and
welcome back to the ask abijit show my
apologies to those of you who are
confused by the timing it's supposed to
start at 9:00 p.m. but I think in the
scheduling I put it at 8:00 p.m. so
apologies to those of you who had to
wait for the show and thank you so much
for waiting and being on this live
stream so I have got a lot of questions
in the comments there's so much
happening in the world and a lot of very
relevant questions that you all have
asked in the comments so I'm going to
take a whole bunch of the questions from
the comments this time and also some
questions from the live chat so that's
what I'm going to do and uh I I do know
that many of you don't have the time to
watch an entire live stre whether it's
live or recorded many of you may not be
interested in every question that I
answer you want to see selected
questions so for those of you who uh
need that I I would like to tell you
that I have this uh Channel called the
abijit Chava Clips channel that is over
here and it's also pinned on top of the
live chat you want to see any question
that have answered any specific question
or clip of that you can check it out
over here uh a bunch of Clips come out
every single day typic Al something that
was answered quite recently in the past
week or so and if you want to search for
something let's say you want to search
for UFOs you can search for UFO for
example and you will get that you want
to search for ISRO you will you can
search for ISRO and find questions about
ISRO search for China you can search
find questions about China and so on so
that's the abijit Chava Clips Channel
Please be aware of that and please go
ahead and subscribe if that's that's
something that interests you all right
so that that's going to be helpful in
case you want answers to specific
questions
all right uh before I begin let me greet
all of you who are there on the live
stream I can see shagun Chopra Ashish
pandel anant Pai Mahesh Patel ombe Kiker
Matrix Jovi J hind arz manticor a
manticor Kush Kushi Sharma Krishna 14
Vin esman sparkling Lotus M kabona
Punjab story sudhindra Desai laan bagar
geopolitical dub RK ch patil Jay diit
Rahul dun Manoj ban jasman Raj Singh
Anand angad Singh oboy ronak J aru and
aian threat Ripper hello STK Bay T meta
XM Yus zus prar Gupta Baba abijit CH
Arin shuo mang cabonia and lots and lots
of other people so uh with that said
let's get into the questions let me take
some questions that you have asked in
the the the comments let's take that a
couple of those in in the beginning and
then we'll take some questions from live
chat and we'll alternate in that manner
so uh let's begin with this question I
mean it's it's an issue that's on top of
everybody's mind these years especially
in the subcontinent so it's by PR Paul
Bangladesh's border guards Crossing into
India to Halt the construction of a Mand
after ethnic cleansing no less is deeply
troubling why does India tolerate such
actions despite the fact that it's well
known that the US may be behind these
provocations is the Biden Administration
trying to stir things up before handing
over to Trump and if that's the case how
much should India tolerate it's hard to
believe that we still live in a truly
Sovereign Nation with these challenges
okay so what's happening in Bangladesh
right now we know there's been a regime
change old news now H gone and Muhammad
yunus this puppet guy has come has been
put in place and he's the face of the
government which is being run by the by
a bunch of uh well forces that are very
strongly inimical to India and very
friendly with Pakistan so like I've said
ton of times Bangladesh is now East
Pakistan and they are provoking India in
a variety of ways the most recent
provocation was Bangladeshi border
guards crossing over into Indian
Territory and halting the construction
of a temple a Hindu
Mand because it's somehow offensive of
them well mind your own business stay in
your territory but yeah they crossed
over and halted the construction of a
temple right and obviously it's such a
long border a very open porous border
that we have with Bangladesh with East
Pakistan that you can't have the BSF and
the Army Etc everywhere at every point
in the border so these sort of things
well they can do it so what should India
do and are we completely important are
we a non-sovereign nation and and what
exactly is happening and a lot of people
are saying that India should think about
military action go ahead and take do
military action and and save the Hindus
there's aind Hindu genocide happening in
Bangladesh lots of Hindus have been
killed lot of atrocities and whatnot and
the media won't report that yeah so all
that is happening so what should India
do should India go ahead and take
military action how long will we
tolerate this that's the question on
everyone's mind so understand
this uh Bangladesh as you all understand
very well they are now a proxy of the US
okay they are a proxy of the US and they
are trying their best to provoke us the
provocations by Bangladesh the objective
is to instigate the Indian public
against the government of India and and
by doing this by instigating the public
and making the Indian Indian citizenry
extremely angry this it's going to it's
going to put a lot of pressure on the
government of India right everyone's
frustrated everyone's tired everyone's
angry so the objective the hope that
they have the bangladeshis okay the
proxies of the US the hope that they
have is that this will pressurize the
government of India enough to force some
kind of military
action Now understand this we have taken
military action in the past
1971 but when we uh liberated East
Pakistan and made converted it to
Bangladesh after military action after
war that war took 8 to n months of very
intense and deliberate planning
preparation
the Indian army in the 71 avoided the
monsoon see Bangladesh is a very
defensible country let's let's take a
look at them okay let's not look at the
map you can look at it in your own free
time Bangladesh is a very defensible
country
geographically it is it has lots of
marshes it has lots of rivers some
rivers are miles
wide it's not a piece of cake to just
walk into the country and and take it of
course it's I it's not like they've got
some very powerful army or anything but
it's a very defensible
country in in the when the Americans
invaded Vietnam they thought it would be
a
walkover and it was a disaster for them
the US military is
incredibly even at that time was
incredibly more powerful than the
Vietnamese military and yet the
vietnames were able to defeat the
Americans so uh that's what we have to
understand if you want to take military
action it's going to take months of
preparation and planning and you're
going to have to do it in a very
specific Manner and they'll be aware of
this right so uh and while we were
planning the war during those eight or
nine months in
1971 about 3 million Hindus were killed
in Bangladesh right and now this action
that we took the military action it it
succeeded to a certain extent it
succeeded because we had help from the
people of
Bangladesh they were tired of the
atrocities commit that the pakistanis
were committing so we had internal help
from Bangladesh from the Bangladesh's
and we obviously armed them the mukti
bahini we created the mukti bahini we
trained the mukti bahini we armed them
they acted as a resistance against the
pakistanis and that obviously had
certain small amount of impact on the
war right and in 71 we our army bypassed
all the all the cities all the towns all
the centers of resistance we bypassed it
all we bypassed all those centers if we
do it again question is what's going to
happen to all the Hindus who are living
there H what's going to happen if we
bypass the cities and we go straight for
Dhaka what will happen in the cities to
the Hindus and in the towns and the
villages we don't think about that right
the thing is thing is we in India we've
watched Hollywood movies
and we think we can behave like the
Americans uh behave in those movies the
real world doesn't work that way we can
certainly flatten a nation like the us
if we want to I mean but do we want to
do that to Bangladesh of course not
that's not how we operate that's not how
civilized people operate right so you do
that there's going to be a Slaughter in
Bangladesh and then the West they are
waiting for this they're waiting for
India to to make make a mistake that's
why they have dislodged Hina evicted her
and replaced her with Mr Muhammad yunus
they their hope is that they can push
India into a conflict and then that will
give them the justification to destroy
India
economically okay India's economy is a
growing economy it's a rising economy
and it's a long-term problem for the
Americans because they don't want any
new Rising economies any new big Nations
any new big econom powerful
Nations so they are waiting for the
chance that gives them the justification
to destroy India's
economy they're waiting for this to
happen and that's why the Bangladesh is
are provoking us Bangladesh is a proxy
just like Ukraine is a proxy in
America's war against
Russia similarly Bangladesh is a proxy
and they want to use Bangladesh against
India the same way they they using
Ukraine against Russia
okay so for so if we do something silly
like military action or something it
will it will be hell for
India and in 1971 the Americans
obviously they were denying they denied
that anybody was being there was any
genocide happening in East Pakistan they
denied that there there was anything
being done against the Hindus atrocities
or genocide or murders or or or
massacres they they they kept on denying
it even though they knew what was
happening and they had the same thing
right now their media is reporting
nothing of what's happening in East
Pakistan so they will say that nothing
is happening and India attacked peaceful
helpless
Bangladesh Hindu nationalist India
attacked peaceful uh helpless Bangladesh
that's what they will say and then they
will throw a ton of sanctions on India
and that will destroy the Indian economy
that is the
objective all right so we in 71 decided
that Bangladesh will be a separate
nation we we had conquered it we were in
Dhaka we had taken control of the entire
nation but we chose to make it into an
to give it its independence we could
have reabsorbed East Bengal at the time
it has always been our territory we
chose to to keep it separate and to give
it Independence well now we have to deal
with the consequences of that action
today Bangladesh is a separate nation
theoretically a Sovereign Nation
practically a US basal a US puppet and
it's a proxy that they using against
India so we are surrounded by two
Nations East Pakistan West Pakistan and
they want us to make a mistake so my
point is sit
back
relax stop getting I know it's it's
obviously painful to see what's being
done to the Hindus but at this point in
time uh we cannot take any over action
we can take covert action possibly which
I will not go into that's up to the
government
we are a Sovereign Nation we very much
are a Sovereign Nation what's happening
is happening outside our
territory so at this point in time we
have to swallow the anger swallow the
pain and do and not give the Americans
the
justification or the pretext to do what
they really are itching to do to damage
India's economy so these provocations
will happen I think the provocations
will escalate we could take some action
localized action against its
provocations to tell them that certain
certain red lines cannot be crossed the
Bangladesh is but that's about it and
even that even if you take action
against the Bangladesh border guards or
something kill a few of those because
they entered our territory it's going to
be an international incident and the
West will condemn condemn
India so that the that is the position
we are in this this at this point in
time the situation calls for calm for
patience
for
restraint bide your time India has to
bide its time we're going to have a lot
of this the next 10 20 years we have to
find a way to navigate the world the
next next 10 20 years there's going to
be increasing pressure upon us and
Bangladesh is one of those focal points
of the pressure so that's the situation
in Bangladesh Visa us and this is what
we have to do so there we are
okay next question very relevant
question a bunch of questions a lot of
people have asked me this so I've taken
two or three of these questions as
something that represents all the all
the questions that people have so Anita
Dian Vikram geopolitical they asked the
question ultimately the Assad regime in
Syria has collapsed as per the news
channels how will this impact the region
geopolitically what is the real agenda
and objectives of the power supporting
Rebel
group why is the Assad Leed government
in Syria losing control over territories
few years ago when Isis tried to do it
uh the Putin interven intervened and
saved the Assad government but why are
the rebels have the rebels being able to
get success this time and what's
turkey's stance in the whole Syria
situation it being a member of NATO is
pressured by the West to act anti-
Russia it is infiltrated with Syrian
refugees and Assad has denied to take
back his own people okay what's
happening Visa turkey what's happening
uh and so on right so that's the
question uh
okay so I think for that we should uh
take a look take a look at the map so
where's the map let me open the map
because the map is our friend and that
helps us understand a lot of things so
uh here's the map let me take the
question off the screen for a while and
let's zoom into where the region that
we're talking about so we're talking
about Syria Syria is this nation that's
in the center of the screen right now
now what's
happened uh last 24 hours the Assad
regime has finally Fallen
uh Bashar al- Assad we don't know about
his whereabouts apparently he took a
plane from Damascus and was going
somewhere but apparently the plane
disappeared of the radar did it crash or
was it was what transponder Switched Off
we don't quite know but his whereabouts
are not known zalai Khal zad is uh
alleging that he may be somewhere in the
UA so there's he hasn't shown any
evidence to substantiate his his claim
but that's what he claimed on Twitter Z
KH khad is the was the US Special
representative for Afghanistan who uh
negotiated with the Taliban and in Doha
and all that right so we don't know
where Assad is but the rebels or the
terrorists or alqaeda or Isis or whoever
they are they are us proxy Force they
have or or Turkish proxy Force whatever
you want to call it they have taken over
uh Syria they probably have taken
control of
Damascus uh so that that is what has
happened so understand what's happened
in the so this is obviously another
successful regime change operation
conducted by the United States these uh
Armed Forces whatever you want to call
them rebranded Isis rebranded Al-Qaeda
and so on they are proxies of the US and
Proxes of turkey the Turks have had a
presence in Northern Syria for quite
some time it's it's a region that's rich
in oil so the Turks have been enjoying
that oil obviously uh and and the
Russians have had a presence in Syria so
so look the civil war in Syria began in
2011 and uh you may remember the time
that alqa was fighting the Syrian
government and Isis suddenly emerged out
of nowhere it was obviously a creation
of the US okay and uh the Assad regime
was under tremendous pressure and then
Putin from the north from Russia stepped
in and he uh saved the Syrian government
the Assad government from from uh being
overthrown the Russians have a naval
base in Latakia and they have an air
base also in in the western uh part of
Syria so that is a question mark now
what's going to happen to the Russian
presence in Syria but overall the
American Proxes have taken over Syria
and as we speak right now when hears one
hears that Israel is now making a move
on Syrian territory they are moving
eastwards Israeli tanks have apparently
crossed cross crossed the line of
control from the Golan Heights into
Syrian territory so uh the Israelis May
create most likely a larger so-called
buffer zone right now by by gobbling up
large parts of Syrian territory so
that's what we're going to see now and
uh the terrorist groups or or or
militant groups that have taken over
Syria they have Clos links with turkey
and obviously the us as well so this is
another successful regim operation by
the US so in the past three or four
years since since 2020 what regime
change operations have we seen in the in
in the overall large Asia region we have
seen a regim change operation in
Afghanistan a Handover of power to the
Taliban by the Americans and the Taliban
are getting weekly stiped and funding
from the US the Taliban are a pro us
regime a US proxy regime so the US has
conducted a successful re operation in
Afghanistan then in 2022 they conducted
a successful regime change operation in
Pakistan by housting Imran Khan and
bringing in a pro us puppet government
then
uh there is this new recent coup in
Bangladesh which has brought in a US
puppet government so India is surrounded
by East and West Pakistan there is an
ongoing operation in Burma it's a proxy
war between American forces and Chinese
proxies and the Americans seem to be
winning and they're trying to carve out
an artificial cooki land for Christ out
of Indian Territory and burmes territory
so that is another operation that is
ongoing
and now we have this regime change
operation in Syria so right now in the
Middle East region in the West Asia
region apart from Iran you only have us
proxies Nations that are firmly on the
side of the US in 2003 they wiped out
the Saddam Hussein
regime and Iraq now is a US proxy with
some amount of influence from Iran
because of the Shia
population but Syria has fallen now so
uh and why did this regime fall the
Bashar alassad regime why did it fall uh
so let's go back to that question why
did this regime fall so the Assad regime
first of all Bashar Al Assad never
wanted to be president okay it's old
history it's nothing to do with what's
happened right now his brother Basel Al
Assad was supposed to be the next
president after his F the father ha Al
Assad would demit office or or pass away
but basal Al Assad died in a car crash
and Bashar Al Assad who was an eye
doctor in London had to reluctantly come
back to Syria and eventually he became
the president uh now the AL Assad family
belongs to the alawi sect in Syria Syria
is a mishmash of various ethnic ethnic
groups and religious groups and the
alawi sect is less than 10% of the
Syrian population but they are the Elite
and they've been ruling Syria for the
past 50 plus years is part of the bath
party it's a dictatorship obviously only
dictatorship Works in West Asia nothing
else works that's the nature of the
region so uh now after the Civil War
started the US mediated us induced Civil
War started in
2011 uh it's because of Russian
intervention and Iranian intervention
that the Assad regime
survived so they have had help from
outside support from outside but did
they have support from
inside they probably did not have
support from within the Syrian
population there must have been lots of
disaffected ethnic groups and whatnot So
eventually uh this happened what's
happened now has happened so Iran has
lost a
huge uh a a very major piece on their
geopolitical chessboard they no longer
have any influence now in Syria Syria is
gone and it was through Syria that they
were able to uh you know
maintain the the hold that they have in
Lebanon or the hisbah and all that so
Syria is gone so they no longer have
physical access to libanon if you look
at the map once again let's go back to
the map um where's the
map let's go back to the
map so if you look at the geography Iran
is the nation in the center West of Iran
you have turkey in the Northwest and you
have Iraq now turkey is an is not a
friendly Nation to Iran by any by any
means but in Iraq the the Iranians have
lots of proxies so they were able to
access Syria via
Iraq in a variety of ways uh clandestine
covered ways over ways whatever and
through Syria they were able to uh have
whatever contacts and access they had to
hisbah in Lebanon now Syria is gone and
Lebanon in Lebanon hisbah is very badly
weakened the West Bank is essentially
destroyed the
Palestinian Hamas uh resistance is
mostly crushed by Israel so all the
Iranian proxies are kind of now
enfeebled or destroyed the last piece of
the puzzle is Yemen the an Allah faction
the the huis which are also an Iranian
proxy but now Iran mostly stands alone
in the
region so it is a victory for the US
it's a victory for Israel Israel will
probably now grab large Bunches of
Syrian territory and call it a buffer
zone okay that's how geopolitics works
so the Americans are making things
happen at a very rapid Pace now and what
next is the
question next I would say is Iran Iran
will now come firmly in the crosshairs
of Israel and the United States now
Russia and China cannot afford to let
Iran fall that's the deal right now so
that is the situation turkey is very
much involved in this turkey some would
say turkey has backstabbed Putin um um
what's his name ERD has backstabbed
Putin or whatever there's
no it's not the case he's simply acting
out of his own interest which Every
Nation does so turkey is involved in
this their proxies are in control in
Syria the Assad regime is gone we don't
know about the whereabouts of Al Assad
and his family but that's where we are
so it's a complete transformation of the
geopolitical balance of power in the
West Asia region it's very much
Advantage us Advantage Israel Russia has
been drawn Russia was bogged has been
bogged down you could say and and
completely preoccupied with the
situation in Ukraine in the meanwhile
Israel smashed Hamas smashed hisbah and
that's how they were able to make this
happen and and it looks like there may
have been some kind of deal that was
offered to the Syrian Army because it
looks like they gave up without a fight
just like the Afghan Army gave up
without a fight to the Taliban the same
sort of thing seems to have happened so
either a deal was given to Assad that
you can will be allow will allow you to
escapee and the same was given to the
Syrian Army apparently lots of tanks
from Syria Syrian Army tanks crossed
over into Iraq apparently so we're not
quite sure what's happened what are the
mechanics and dynamics of what has
happened what was the deal that was
offered or not eventually maybe some
clarity may come a few years down the
line but that's where we are so the
whole balance of power now has changed
it's very strongly Advantage us and
Israel in West Asia and this affects the
rest of the world in a variety of ways
so that's situation and we'll keep a
watch on this we'll keep an eye on
this okay Mr 88 says does India's
independent foreign policy also hinder
its power projection capability in the
neighboring region the fact that Nations
like Nepal mes Bangladesh Etc can make
statements and do activities that are
against India's interest is this a
byproduct of keeping an open foreign
policy with the whole world what's the
reason that despite being one of the
strongest militaries in the world the
fastest growing large economy in the
world except the quad growth LOL we
can't use our hard power against those
who are nothing in front of us
okay so is India's independent
independent foreign policy the cause of
this the situation we find ourselves in
if you look uh at the map of the Indian
subcontinent let's do it again map of
the subcontinent if we look at the map
of the subcontinent so East Pakistan
West Pakistan they are not our friends
okay they are proxies of the US
Nepal has kind of transformed into a
proxy of China okay Afghanistan is a
proxy of the US they not anti India as
such but they are a proxy of the US uh
Bhutan is still friendly with us Sri
Lanka you could say proxy of the US
Maldives proxy of China Myanmar there's
a fight going on about about the fate of
Myanmar so we are in we are essentially
surrounded by proxies of more powerful
Nations now in the world today there are
only three nations that have more hard
power than
India these three nations are China
Russia and the US China is about three
and a half times more powerful than
India Russia is about we could say three
times more powerful than China and the
US is about twice as powerful as
Russia so if you give a hard power score
us is 91 or 92 Russia is about 55 China
is about 16 or 17 IND India is about 4.9
that's the score so the problem India is
facing is that if we remove the
influence of China and the us from the
subcontinent India is the Undisputed
boss of the subcontinent and none none
of these nations will dare to do what
they're doing but because they have the
umbrella of protection that is given by
more powerful Nations than India that's
why India is it finds itself in the
situation that it does so this the
situation that we face that Bangladesh
does this and Pakistan does that and
Nepal does this and Sri Lanka does that
and Maldives does that whatever this
situation is not because of an
independent foreign policy it's because
of where we stand VAV hard
power that's the only factor that
matters in geopolitics is hard power an
independent foreign policy is a good
thing it shows that India is a genuinely
Sovereign Nation otherwise we would not
even have an independent foreign policy
so the independent foreign policy is not
something that hinders our power
projection the the amount of hard power
the lack of hard power compared to these
other nations that's what hinders our
power projection capability in our
neighboring region China is like three
and a half four times more powerful than
us the US is 20 times more powerful than
than us roughly roughly and they
have unlimited power projection
capabilities that's why in our own
neighborhood they're able to have these
small Nations act like bullies against
us and say all kinds of things and do
all kinds of actions and all that the
only thing that b in geopolitics is hard
power you can have any kind of foreign
policy you want but the fact that India
India has an independent foreign policy
is a good thing it shows that we are
still a Sovereign Nation we are
genuinely Sovereign Nation there are
only four nations that are genuinely
Sovereign in the world every other
nation is is not entirely Sovereign
let's just put it that way so yeah
that's the reason why we we are in the
situation that we are in so the sit the
solution to the problem is for India to
increase its hard power and the
straightforward way to do that is by
increasing the size of its economy
economic growth with economic growth
comes mil comes an increase in military
spending power which gives you a more
powerful military and economic economic
power plus military power is essentially
hard power plus the amount of nukes you
have and all that but that's another
Factor so the solution for India is to
keep growing its economy no matter what
happens for the next 20 years long
process but that's the only solution to
India's
problems okay Vikram geopolitical says
we can see many Indian origin people
taking influential positions in Trump's
cabinet is Trump trying to impress the
Indian American community in the US or
some other reason
Trump has no reason to impress
anybody least of all India or
Indians what will he gain by impressing
Indians Indians are not politically
significant in the US Indians aren't
aren't as powerful political voting
block Indians vote very democratically
you cannot you know trying to unify and
unite Indians is like hering cats you
can her sheep you can even her cows and
buffalo and other animals camels goats
whatever you can't h
cats cats every single cat has a mind of
its own you simply can't get 20 cats
together and make them walk in the same
direction they'll all go in their own
way so trying to unite Indians is like
hurting cats and that because of that
Indians are despite having despite being
a sign reasonably good percentage
percentage of the US population we are
in politically insignificant we simply
don't unite and we are politically well
the way it is right so this no need for
Trump to try and impress Indians or
please Indians Indian in the Indian
American community in the US he simply
is uh hiring these people and nominating
them for these positions because they're
good Indians are becoming more relevant
in the US even though they're
politically insignificant individual
Indians lots of them are very relevant
in in various ways lots of Indian CEOs
and so on and then you have people who
are now entering politics VI ramaswami
back ramaswami is one of them and so on
and uh
so in Trump's cabinet who all do we have
who's of Indian origin we have JD Van's
wife who's the second lady she's not
politically active but yeah she's a
second lady Usha Vance she's of Indian
origin then you have um you have vivac
ramaswami is going to be Mr number two
in the department of govern government
efficiency Doge he going to report to
Elon Musk as eventually that's vac then
you have cash Patel Kash Patel who is
now the boss of the FBI he's been
nominated to be the boss the director of
the FBI very powerful position and then
we have Tuli gabard who's not of Indian
origin but she's a Hindu and she's going
to be the boss of the entire
intelligence apparatus in the US so
she's going to be kab Patel's boss very
powerful very very powerful position so
yeah and I can't think of anybody else
but in in case there is there's somebody
we we'll find out so lots of Indian
origin people lots of many not lots of
but
very some very important positions have
been given to either Indian origin
people
or Hindu people right uh so yeah it's
because they are genuinely good and
they're relevant not because Trump is
trying to please anybody not at
all um I was hoping somebody would ask
me questions about UFOs but I'm not
getting getting any questions about UFOs
so so I to pick a question from seven
months ago but usfos are very relevant
right now so this is a question
by what do you think of the UFO
disclosure stuff going on in the US I
personally am very suspect I'd like your
take if you have delved into it so I
have those who have been watching
hopefully I'm audible now hopefully
hello one second let me see I think I'm
audible now yeah there was a slight
disconnection but we're good
now okay UFOs
what's going on in the US there has been
this Spate of UFO sightings UAP
sightings whatever you want to call it
all over the place and it's I mean those
of you who know me and who have been
following me for some time will know
that I am a very big UFO
skeptic I am not a Believer yes some the
truth is out there in UFOs exist and
Aliens Exist I am an extremely skeptical
person I've said that over and over
again
but now I'll tell you what I'm convinced
of at least one thing this phenomenon is
there now it's all over the place I've
live news broadcasts have captured UFOs
flying around in the air multiple UFOs
and there's videos all over Twitter
taken by Ordinary People in New Jersey
New York in the US and the UK and what
all kinds of other places of these
phenomena in the air these objects that
are flying around in the air in the
skies in the in space or wherever it is
so it's very clear now that the UFO or
UAP phenomenon is a fact there's just
way too much evidence now to disregard
that so now I can tell you that I agree
after seeing the incredible amount of
evidence that's come out in the past few
weeks and months I agree now that the
UFO phenomenon is a genuine phenomenon
and it's something that we need to
try and understand what what on Earth is
going on what is going on right now the
question is what are these UFOs or
uips
so we find people who take out their
cell phones and capture these events
these phenomena you see lights flying
around the sky you see various shapes of
the UFOs uh some of them are round some
of them are I I saw a video taken from
from an airplane cockpit from a
commercial jet of a cube shaped UFO
zipping past the aircraft uh I've seen
uh things of all shapes and sizes you
know star shaped UFOs with a circle
thing going on in inside all kinds of
Lights I even seen in the past two three
days uh videos of UFOs that are shaped
exactly like aircraft in the night sky
you can see the shape of the lights they
seem to have wings they even make the
sound that that an airliner will make
but the
lights are non-standard
lights air commercial aircraft or
private aircraft or military aircraft
don't have those lights those colors and
that configuration and
those Jet Plane like UFOs they make
turns that jet planes can't make
ridiculously sharp turns so something is
going on now what are the how could we
possibly explain what are the
possible explanations of this phen of
these phenomena one explanation is that
the United States or and maybe other
countries some other
countries have
developed
technologies that we are not aware of
extremely advanced technology that is
kind of on on the border between fact
and science
fiction um maybe some kind of way of
manipulating gravity perhaps we're not
sure what it is
but the the way these things move it
defies uh our understanding of
conventional physics neutronian
physics so and we we see some of these
objects even emerging from from the
ocean or diving into the sea into the
ocean so these could be objects that can
uh navigate the skies as as the space
the space the sky the atmosphere and
even the oceans
so what are the possible explanations
one is is that governments have access
to incredibly advanced technology and
it's Al secret programs maybe the us
maybe Russia China maybe some other
countries that's one explanation maybe
it's just technology advanced technology
maybe loed Martin technology or or NASA
technology or whatever you want to
believe General atomics whatever that's
one explanation the second explanation
is that it's actually aliens but I would
um and look
I was in Hong Kong last week last
weekend that's why I did not do the live
stream here I was on a uh you could say
a diplomatic trip and I I met a
gentleman from France there okay and
that gentleman
is he has been following this thing as
well for a very long time and he's
convinced that there are there's alien
involvement in this that we have been
contacted by by uh Alien beings and they
have shared some technology or we have
acquired some technology from crashed
craft of theirs and that's been reversed
engineered and that's how some countries
a few select countries have access to
these technology that's another
explanation that is given now I Am
Naturally very skeptical person and I
would prefer to give more Credence to
the to the possibility that it is uh
simply human technology but very
advanced technology but something is
happening and whoever is operating this
craft they have decided that now they'll
make it very public earlier it was very
hard to get high quality or any quality
footage of UFOs now it's all over the
place just go on Twitter and you see
you'll see it everywhere so it
definitely exists these whether they are
drones or craft or whatever you want to
call them let's call them UFOs these
UFOs they represent extremely advanced
technology that regular conventional
physics that we are aware of of cannot
explain so it's either governments that
have somehow
developed a technology that that are
Beyond what's taught in physics
Universities at the highest levels or
it's
aliens there is and and there is then
talk about you know all kinds of
speculation on Twitter and all that
maybe uh we are being considered for to
become uh for membership in in a
Galactic Federation or something look
there's no evidence for that so
something is is happening right now
UFO's all over the place in the US
especially of over New Jersey Etc but
the government is
quiet they they have been found hovering
over Air Force bases military
installations in the US the UK as
well they've been witnessed in Argentina
and other countries as well but we
currently have no explanation of what
these things are so maybe something some
kind of revelation will happen some kind
of disclosure will happen soon maybe
they're preparing the public for this we
don't quite know so my point is let's
wait and watch but it's there it is
definitely true can't deny it
anymore okay Sumit Agarwal says what's
your view on the BJP officially accusing
the US State Department of destabilizing
India has the US The Tipping Point on
interference look I this is definitely
not a political matter it's a
geopolitical matter that's why I'm
talking about this uh I generally don't
comment about BJP Congress all that
stuff all the internal politics matter
but in this case the BJP has officially
gone ahead and accuse the US state
department and George Soros Etc of of of
being involved in various activities uh
aimed at destabilizing
India so why have they done this what's
the point of this has the US crossed
some Tipping Point or red
line I don't
know what to make of it
really uh you know there's a difference
between words and actions if they have
crossed a certain red line and they've
crossed a Tipping Point then instead of
talking we should take some
action the government which is ruled run
by the BJP which is ruled by the BJP the
BJP is in power of the government the
government should take some actual
action some steps on the ground aimed at
ending the US interference and U the
steps they are taking to destabilize
India what's the point of putting out
statements and and engaging in a war of
words what's the
point what what are they trying to
achieve what outcome will it will it
bring in it will simply
simply the only reaction you'll see is
denials and the action on the ground
will
continue so I don't understand what this
is all
about we all know what the US is doing
we all know what us proxies are doing in
the subcontinent and so on so if the
government is aware of it which it looks
like it finally is then it should take
some actual action steps on the
ground what's the point of words of
engaging in a war of words on Twitter or
X what's the point I don't get it I it's
it's actually disappointing I would like
to see action on the ground aimed at
ending us interference in India and
actions that destabilize India Why Us
proxies take action on the
ground so much can be
done but right now we just seeing a war
of words so that doesn't impress me much
unfortunately okay prai Paul says why is
it that IND despite its vast talent pool
and unique geographical challeng
geopolitical challenges hasn't produced
a figure like Elon Musk someone who not
only drives technological breakthroughs
but also shapes narratives and takes
bold stances on National issues is it
due to systemic barriers cultural
mindset or lack of encouragement for
individuals to step into such
influential roles why don't we see such
voices actively addressing and
championing Indian concerns on a global
stage there's so many reasons for that
um we have a vast tarent pool right so
many brilliant young students graduate
every year and what do they do the best
of the lot want to just get out of the
country immigrate immigrate to the US or
the West whatever excuse me nobody wants
to stay in India because they know that
India doesn't respect Talent OR Merit
it's not like we Indian citizens hate
talent and Merit it's just that the
system is constructed in such a way
that Merit is sought out and destroyed
me Talent is sought out and destroyed
and the system doesn't recognize
Merit it doesn't reward you based on
your performance it rewards you based on
quotas and whatnot so in such a in such
a system the best talent will
leave that's the first reason for that
and then when it comes to doing business
and all that there are so many problems
in doing business in India the
government of India has not done enough
to make India a great place for doing
business lots of Indian entrepreneurs
once they make it big they move to
places like the the UAE to Dubai or the
Abu Dhabi or to Singapore and that's
where they incorporate their companies
outside of India so that the the Indian
taxation regime doesn't apply to
them imagine it's it's
better it's it's it makes more business
sense for an Indian R preneur to
incorporate a company in Singapore than
to incorporate it in India why has the
government created this environment and
this sort of Taxation and so on regime
why why can't we make things better and
then there's all the the bureaucracy the
red tape so it's nothing to do with
Indian culture it's something to it's
everything to do with the Indian system
the colonial system that we are laboring
under that is breaking the backs of the
Indian economy of the Indian
entrepreneur and the Indian people
in the US they welcome people like ilas
they welcome talented people and they
reward them based on their
performance so the the
Americans respect Merit they respect
Talent it's a meritocratic
society and in the US you can rise as
high as you can based on the amount of
work you do and the kind of the quality
of work you do and that's why people
like K mus people who want to do great
work they are attracted to places like
the US so why can't we make India that
sort of
society I know it's not easy but why
that's why the government exists that's
why we vote for them so it's been like a
while since this government has been in
power more than a decade now uh it's
it's high time they do something about
this so that these are the reasons why
despite the vast talent that exists in
India we don't see people like Elon Musk
you know rising up we don't see Elon
Musk kind of people in India we don't
see SpaceX in
India why don't we have a SpaceX in
India why don't we have multiple space
xes why don't we have Microsoft inan
Microsoft Indian Google Indian apple
Indian Tesla why don't we have any of
these things because we encourage the
system is such that it pushes people
away you can't succeed in India get out
and succeed there and then we will give
you you a padmashri or padmabhushan or
something if you so we will reward you
for leaving India that's the kind of
system we have it's terrible that's why
and it's frustrating but
yeah okay space Dian
and rittik achara okay with SpaceX
launching Rockets almost weekly India
launching Rockets almost in every 3
months no bigger Rockets being developed
what do you you think India will lose a
space race is there seems to be no
ambition among the political class and
the second question is ISRO has updated
the timeline of Kagan to 2025 end the
end of 2025 what could be the reasons
and how should India be more ambitious
citing respon respite from us uh also
how many space projects India must
expect to at least reach moon or Mars
with men women by the end of this
decade so where is India in the space
race race so first of all um
let's let's go and see okay how many
missions has is is done so let let me
look for that let's let me bring that on
the
screen ISRO missions accomplished
and let me put that on the screen how
many missions has ISRO conducted thus
far missions accomplished by is let's
take the question uh there we
go uh so how many how many Rockets has
ISRO launched thus far ISRO apparently
has launched 98 Rockets okay dating back
to 1979 from 1979 to 2024 end ISRO has
launched 98
Rockets 98 Rockets now let's do the same
thing for Space X Space
X let's do the same thing for Space X
I'm going to go and search for Space
X uh Space X Space X launches okay let
me put the Space X Launches on the
screen shall
we so ISRO
98 thus far from 1979 onwards ISRO and
SpaceX where is it where is
it SpaceX was incorporated as a company
in 2006 I believe since 2006 419
launches 381 total Landings 352 total
ref flights
and uh if you look at the starlink uh
data it's even more ridiculous right
so that is the situation ISRO since 1979
has 98 launches SpaceX since
2006 has 419 rocket launches 381
Landings we don't even have a
land a reusable rocket that can land on
its own and then the question question
of refights doesn't even
occur right so uh that is the
situation okay where where are we the
question here we are so where is India
in the Space Race uh to be very honest
India isn't a participant in the Space
Race India is simply trying to achieve
some small little objectives in a few
years we will have a human being orbit
the Earth or maybe three people orbit
the Earth from the gagan capsule
that was first accomplished in the 1960s
or 50s whever it was 50s 60s we are
trying to do that now then by the end of
this decade by the 2030s we will have a
small space station that was achieved in
in the second half of the 20th century
then by 2040 or something we'll put a
person on the
moon that was also achieved in
1969 and Mars we're not even thinking
about Mars we don't have an integrated
long-term step by step
St space program we have one mission to
Venus one another mission coming up to
Mars in some time we have a half haard
Space
Program our space program isn't aligned
with the Indian national interest or
India's geopolitical priorities we don't
see space is space as an integral
component of our geopolitical
plans we don't have ambition I'm not
criticizing ISRO I'm criticizing the
government of India ISRO can only do
what the government approves they can
maybe put proposals but the government
has its own way of looking at things so
I have said many times that ISRO doesn't
have a significant budget and the ISRO
Chief the head of ISRO uh he at some
point in time had come on the ranir show
Ran's podcast and ranir asked this
question because I've discussed this
with rir many times so ranir asked my
question to the chairman of
iso uh Dr snat
and Dr somat said that
ISRO often cannot complete cannot use up
all the money that's budgeted that's
that's allocated to it in it in its
budget and sometimes at the end of the
year it has to return some of the money
to the government so does it mean that I
am wrong and that ISRO has all the
budget it needs it doesn't mean that it
means that only certain missions are
approved and for that a certain budget
is
given but the mission so the project for
creating a heavy launch vehicle that is
10 times more powerful than the current
gslv that project doesn't exist so then
how can there be a budget for
that the mission for developing reusable
Rockets doesn't exist so how will you
have a budget for that so the modest
little missions that are approved there
is sign there is sufficient budget for
that
only so there's no ambition from the
government
the ISRO engineers and scientists can
do can can can undertake even very
ambitious missions they've demonstrated
the
capability so so we are not in the Space
Race we are
simply an
afterthought we
India very disappointed to see the
government's attitude towards space very
disappointing India has the potential to
be a major space power but now we are so
far behind SpaceX is a private company
that was incorporated in
2006 and it has launched what four times
more Rockets than ISRO has launched
since
1979 more than four times the rockets
and they now have the most powerful
rocket ever constructed ever
designed and we are still trying we
still have to take the help of SpaceX or
or Aran or whatever to launch certain
satellites because our most powerful
rocket can't launch can't handle that
weight can't we develop more powerful
Rockets of course we can we can have it
ready in the next three years if you
give the sufficient sufficient budget
and you have an ambitious time and you
can develop a rocket that's 10 times
more powerful in in three years just see
how rapidly SpaceX has developed more
and more powerful
Rockets the Starship the first test was
in 2019
it was a brick it was a can on on Wheel
on on four legs or three legs with a
with a with a rocket engine at the
bottom it was not even shaped like a
rocket and today in 24 about five years
later they have the most powerful rocket
in the
world that's how quickly they're able to
develop technology can't we do that of
course we can but we don't want to the
government doesn't want it so what can I
say about it
and yeah so we can certainly reach the
moon I would say we can reach the Moon
by 2035 I I would say that chundra and
10 should be a a man Mission To The Moon
we can certainly do that by
2025 we can reach Mars by let's say 2045
or something SpaceX will reach Mars by
the end of this decade so we are way
behind we don't even have a Mars mission
right now M Mars mission no one is even
thinking about it so we are far behind
we certainly have the ability to catch
up very rapidly but the government
doesn't seem to care about
it what can I say that that's that's
where we stand right now in the
so-called Space
Race okay ainka says is democracy still
alive is democracy still alive there is
no such thing as as real
democracy okay democracy is a sham
let me tell you why I say
this what does democracy mean it means
that every citizen of the country who is
past a certain age adulthood 18 let's
say every citizen of the country gets to
participate in the electoral process
every citizen gets to vote every citizen
has the right to vote and in elections
and every citizen has the right to stand
for
election that's what it means now
now and and the theory is that every
citizen will vote for a candidate or a
party that according to him or
her is doing the best for the country's
National
interest the best possible party so the
theory is that every
person understands what the Indian
national interest is and knows which
party political party or candidate is
best aligned with the Indian national
interest that's the theory now in
practice does any Indian citizen know
what the Indian national interest is is
is this something that's taught in
school in college in
University what is the national interest
no one has the foggiest understanding or
idea of what the national interest
is and every nation has a different set
of interests India's national interest
will be very different from Israel's
National interest or the American
national interest or the Canadian
national interest or the Chinese
National interest so my national
interest is different from the interest
of other nations you to understand
exactly what your National interest
is and that to understand that you to
understand international relations you
to understand geopolitics you to
understand the current threat scenario
in climate you to understand economics
basic economics you to understand so
many things for that you need to be
educated and even if you have a master's
degree the Indian education teach system
doesn't teach you any of these
things
so for a democracy to work really work
each citizen needs to be well
educated is that the situation in India
today no no no
no and secondly we are assuming that
each citizen will prioritize the
national interest and make and vote for
the party or the candidate that best
alliance with the national interest but
is that the case in India in India we
vote on the basis of region on language
on religion on cast there are
certain voting groups that votee
for interests and agendas that don't
align with the national interest maybe
oppose the national interest is that
democracy this is not democracy it's a
joke so what's the solution
so in Greece ancient Greece they say
that Greece was the birthplace of
democracy right in ancient Greece who
could vote could women vote am I saying
women should not vote I'm not saying
that okay by the way I'm just saying
let's take a look at ancient Greece in
ancient Greece the Greeks probably
believed that women were not intelligent
okay they probably believed that so
women could not vote secondly peasants
could not vote so who could vote in
Greece in elections only only the
wealthy could vote only the Nobles and
the wealthy land owners could vote
that's about 2 to 5% of the population
because these people actually understood
the world they understood economics they
understood the threats to the nation
they understood international relations
and all that so only those people who
genuinely had an understanding of these
things were allowed to vote in Ancient
India dating back to even before Greece
who could vote in Ancient India we had
the imperial system we had Emperors and
kings and queens right you could not
vote against
them you could not you cannot vote to
depose the emperor doesn't work so what
could you vote for you could vote for
you could elect your
local uh Representatives your local uh
Village level administrators and all
that because most people understand
what's happening around them oh my
garbage isn't being taken out every day
or or the the drains are are not taken
not cleaned properly every week or
whatever or uh the there is corruption
in the in the marketplace or whatever so
the local things people understand so
you could vote for your local officials
and that's it you cannot vote for the
people up high so you could vote for
your local officials you could elect you
could elect them into power or you could
throw them out of power through your
vote in India that's the kind of
democracy we had in India it was a
hybrid system imperial system up top and
locally you had
democracy but over here in India every
five years you can throw out the
government you can throw out the prime
minister is democracy still alive there
is no such thing as democracy there is
no real democracy it's all
sham India is more democratic than
Nations like the US in the US you have
this artificial two-party system and no
matter who you come who you vote for
president there is an unelected power
center that always
continues to exist and they always look
out for the US geopolitical interest and
overall National interest so uh and if a
certain president tries to do certain
things that are not in line with what
they perceive as the US national
interest is then they don't allow the
president to to really get things done
so nowhere in the world do you have a
real
democracy that's simply the fact of the
world democracy doesn't mean that you
get to vote once in five years and done
ah I could vote so so it's democracy
that's a
joke there are so many nations whose
entire political system was created by
by
by by occupiers their constitution was
written by occupiers their legal system
the laws were written by occupiers
they're not allowed to change the
Constitution but they're allowed to vote
once in five
years and only certain kinds of
politicians are allowed to exist other
politicians they get bumped off you call
that a
democracy there is no democracy in the
real in the world India may be the
closest you have to a democracy a very
chaotic democracy elections every other
week in some state or some place of some
part of India and people who are not
even literate but they will vote for
whoever they think is right and people
vote some people vote as a single voting
block you know vote Bank voting and all
so even India is not a proper democracy
this is not how democracy is supposed to
be so is democracy still alive no it was
never alive democracy never really
existed it's not the best form of
government the best form of government
what is it it is a benevolent
dictatorship an enlightened benevolent
dictatorship a dictator like Lewan Yu or
Tundra Gupta
Maia or keska the great or the great
Gupta Emperors or Lord
Ram dictators who actually care for the
civilization for the nation and for the
people
and they can get things done with one
order that's the best form of government
the problem with the system of
government is that when there's a
transfer power from
one from one Monarch or one dictator to
another if the wrong kind of person
comes to power then you are in there you
are in deep trouble if somebody like K
comes to power somebody like danand
comes to power you in deep deep
trouble so there is there are pros and
cons of all systems but democracy nah
it's not alive it's all a joke it's all
a
sham okay I've taken a lot lot of
questions from the comments let's take
some questions from the live
chat okay Nicks says does do I think
India will benefit from a benevolent
dictatorship ask yourselves how was
India during the marata Empire India was
great India was doing greater under the
during the marata Empire how was India
doing under the uh rule of
uh of Ashok the great chra Gupta Maia
India was doing great India benefited
from these this rule how did India do
Under keska The Great my goodness India
India did supremely well under keska the
great great how did India do Under the
rule of the Gupta Emperors golden age of
India how did India do Under the rule of
let's say uh the Chas rajaj Chula
rajendra chulah brilliant
India certainly will benefit from B
dictatorship but we don't have that
so
uh okay next let's take a couple more
questions on the live chat Raji says why
is the US trying to destabilize Georgia
is the recent FDA with India one of the
reasons nah it has nothing to do with
India absolutely nothing to do with
India okay let's go to the map and let's
find out where Georgia is yes where is
Georgia is this nation yes Georgia is a
small nation in the Caucasus Reg
what's the Caucasus region the region
between the Black Sea and the Caspian
Sea the Sea of Kap and the Black Sea so
this is Georgia it is south of Russia
north of Armenia Northwest of aeran
northeast of turkey that's Georgia and
Georgia has had its problems with Russia
and so on so what the US wants is a very
strongly Pro us proxy puppet government
in Georgia that's what they want and
it's not about D stabilizing Georgia
it's about having it's about expanding
the sphere of
influence it's about power projection so
you take over Georgia by having a puppet
regime installed there then you can
expand power further north right up to
Russia's borders and that's why you do
it so yeah there is a regime change
operation that's going on right now in
Georgia so the short answer is that they
are do doing this
to expand their sphere of influence
that's why they're doing
it VII says democracy is not working for
me what should I do it's not working for
any of
us what can we do right now we are
powerless the citizens of the country
are powerless the best you can do is you
can elect the best possible uh
government the best possible candidates
and then hope for things to change there
are certain things people the ordinary
people can't do a thing
about unless you want to get involved in
El Al politics and all but that's again
you are in then you go inside the system
the democratic
system um the ordinary citizen across
the world whether it's India whether
it's the European Union France Germany
wherever US Canada wherever you are the
ordinary
citizen is powerless to change the
system it's the kind of time we are born
in so uh there's nothing you can do
about it actually the only thing you can
do is vote wisely and hopefully over
time the system changes in the right
kind of system eventually emerges for
for the right kind of system to emerge
in India we would want to transition to
a presidential form of government that
is way closer to a much more efficient
form of government than the Westminister
system that we have right now where we
can't even elect directly the leader of
the country you can only vote for your
local representative and the
representatives get together the on were
elected to vote the to to select the
Prime Minister that's a very indirect
form of governance that that kind of um
renders the people powerless to decide
their own fate so the first thing that
needs to happen in the transition to a
better form of government is a
presidential form of government for that
to happen you will need a very strong
leader to come to power so and that will
take some time so the only thing you can
do is vote very wisely be very careful
about who you vote for
okay um some more questions from the
live chat and I'll go back to the
comments after
that
uh let us
see dunar Singh Johan says you once
mentioned that cell phone radiation is
not dangerous but the newer Studies have
proved how electromagnetic force from
cell phones actually disrupts
mitochondrial functioning leading to DNA
mutations and cancer so I must have said
that a two ago based on what information
was available then if newer Studies have
come out saying something else then I'll
have to check it out right the thing
about science is that nothing can be
considered to be the permanent forever
truth okay
facts the facts that are available today
may be replaced by better facts from
better research that are available
available next year or the year after
that our understanding of the world keep
keeps changing
evolving more studies are done every
year and then we may discover something
new so maybe a couple of years ago what
we knew was that cell phone radiation
the electromagnetic signals are not
harmful but maybe they are maybe new
research is proven so I haven't seen
this what you what you're referring to
but I will check it out I will I'll not
do a Google Search right now or whatever
search because it'll take time and but
yeah thank you for bringing this to
everyone's notice and I will certainly
check it out and if I find something
that does corroborate what you say then
I'll certainly discuss it in probably
the next live stream so appreciate you
bringing this to our
attention all right um let's go back to
the comments we took some questions from
the comments and here we
go rudrajit sarar asks wonderful
questions I think I should do a couple
of episodes only from the question he
asks because he asked so many wonderful
question like 20 30 of them so I will
take this one why didn't the Europeans
settle in large numbers in Africa like
like they did in America and Oceania so
we know that the Europeans are settled
in the Americas they conquered the
Americas they displaced the they
replaced the natives and today if you
look at the Americas North America South
America a significant percentage of the
population is of European origin you
look at oan oan which is mainly
Australia New Zealand a significant
percentage majority of the population is
of European origin right so they settled
down in the Americas they settled down
in Australia and New Zealand why not
Africa why not
India they could have done the same
thing if the Europeans wanted after they
took control complete control of India
they could have annihilated the Indian
population and they could have settled
on in India and the same thing they
could have done in Africa they had
complete control over Africa why didn't
they settle there they treated India as
a place from where to extract unlimited
quantities of resources and they
enriched themselves immensely as a
consequence and the same thing about
Africa huge continent the largest
continent full of natural resources and
the exploited that to their heart's
content why didn't they settle down
there climate very simple the
Europeans uh the colonizers were of What
ethnicity
uh initially it was the
Spanish then it was uh the Italians some
Italians as well and you had the Dutch
you had the Danes to some extent Denmark
and then you had the British the anglos
the
Anglo-Saxons these folks even the
Germans the
belgians and I'm sure there's more okay
but you get the point All European
nations now if you look at a map of
Europe yeah let's go to the map let's
see see what kind of place they live in
they live in higher latitudes if you if
you look at the southernmost point of
Spain it's at the Latitude 36 point
something and typically it's if you look
at England London the latitude is 51
they come from very cold places and they
can't hot climate isn't good for them
they they it's it's not something to
enjoy so about 100,000
Englishmen educated and controlled the
whole of India but uh they preferred to
live in Hill stations and all and they
did not enjoy the hot climate that is
that exists in the southern parts of
India they didn't like it same for Burma
Etc and Africa has all kinds of climate
but very hot climate overall equatorial
and tropical and so on and then you have
the Sahara desert climate in the um and
so on so the climate is something that
did not agree with them when it comes to
North America the climate was much more
like what they are used to in in Europe
right
especially you knowwhere and and even
when it comes to
Australia the majority of the continent
is empty the Europeans have only settled
in the Southern and Eastern parts of
Australia the cooler parts of Australia
if you look at uh Melbourne the the you
can see that the latitude is- 38 if you
look at cine it's uh- 3 3 Brisbane is
kind of hot atus 27 even that is cool
climate actually and let's not talk
about ad late because of what happened
today but yeah and New Zealand is a
pretty cold country so they prefer to
settle down permanently in uh places
that had climates that they were
accustomed to and the other places they
preferred to colonize and and and occupy
and uh exploit extraction but not
settled down permanently I think it had
a lot to do with
climate right more questions more
questions uh Deo 9 something 9 Deo 9234
says what's your take on Putin's recent
advice to a German entrepreneur to be
proud in speaking German instead of
English English as he belongs to a
Sovereign Nation that's whose native
language is German not English is trying
to reignite the long slept proud
nationalistic sentiment among the
Germans as their election is on the
cards as we all know Germany is Europe's
economic Powerhouse which is currently
going downhill
look first of all there has to be a
personal angle so Putin spent a lot of
time in East Germany as a KGB officer
Putin speaks German
fluently uh
so and he probably at at some level in
his heart may have some kind of
affection for the German language
so maybe that's one of the reasons why
he said this the other thing is that is
look we all know I hope you all know
Germany is not a Sovereign Nation
Germany is under permanent us
occupation
so maybe it's just reminding Germany
that you were once Sovereign you know
and you should have respect for your own
language
um so uh I don't think he's trying to
reignite anything it's not possible
Germany is too deeply under us
occupation uh the nationalistic
sentiment won't be reignited there's too
many immigrants who've come into Germany
and there's no nationalism possible once
the percentage of immigrants goes past a
certain Tipping Point or whatever uh
yeah election on the cards but I assure
you whoever comes to power will be very
strongly Pro Us in the in in the
whenever the next election is so it will
make no difference to Germany's a
geopolitical uh stance it'll go exactly
the way the way the West the US intends
so maybe just trying to remind the
Germans to be a little more proud of
their own language and all but it's not
going to make too much of a difference
in
Germany okay rudrajit sarar says why
does why do our school textbooks try to
portray that before the arrival of the
British India was underdeveloped poor
uncivilized uneducated backward Etc it's
understandable from western books books
but why do Indian books do this Indian
School text books you
see in the abrahamic
world you the west Western Europe the
West entire Europe Etc Europe America
and all that these are part of the
western world and they are part of the
abrahamic world and in the abrahamic
world there is a before and after
division where does this division happen
it's before
Christianity and after Christianity so
let's say we're talking about England
England becomes Christian in the middle
of the first Millennium ad in the second
half of the first Millennium ad that's
when England starts becoming Christian
and it's almost fully christianized by
ad so they regard everything that
existed before Christianity as paganism
which is barbaric
and the same attitude exists in all
other European cultures that whatever
culture religion practices we had before
Christianity was paganism it was
barbaric It's associated with Satanism
and all that so in the old Indo European
culture that we Indians are part of and
we probably are the progenitors of that
in the old Indo European culture women
had the important role of healers they
were the guardians of the ancient herbal
knowledge which we call aured in India
and uh they played important roles as
priestesses as as healers as midwives
and whatnot all those things so the
traditional knowledge of
healing was was the domain of
women okay and the same was there in
Europe after
Christianity became the dominant
religion in Europe Europe uh
Christianity sees the abrahamic
religions see women as
inferior but having this incredible
knowledge made them very powerful in
society women were highly regarded in
Indo European
Society right they were healers they
could save your
life so that gave them a position of
power so what the church did was they
termed such women as witches women who
sort with the devil they have this
satanic knowledge and all that so burn
them as witches so that's how the
old culture was destroyed Stamped Out
and and in the modern in the 20th
century in today's world all that was is
regarded as paganism people who have
such ancient knowledge were called
witches and everything that came before
Christianity that existed before
Christianity is regarded as barbaric and
the same applies to I'm sure Islam as
well I think in Islam they call the
pre-islamic era of Arabia is what jilia
or something which is like
uh uh barbaric era or
something so the same was then applied
to
India through the economic system so in
the ecademic system a similar thing was
applied so the in in India under the
British colonial education system
everything European everything Western
was raised the the British occupation of
of India was was termed as benevolent
and and something that that served to
uplift India from barbarity and
primitive uh
primitivity and uh obviously they will
portray Indian culture as backward
misogynistic uncivilized uneducated poor
barbaric all that in in subtle
ways and the same thing has continued
after 1947 we haven't changed our
education system at all the same
attitudes the
same same thing has persisted so even
today the say that's what Indian
textbooks do that's what they say that
the British came on a great civilizing
Mission we Indians were poor backward
miserable barbaric primitive
misogynistic patriarchal
casst of whatever else and the English
civilized us so that's the same thing
that you will see in Indian textbooks
today it's a same thing about before and
after in Europe it's it's about before
Christianity which is the Pagan era and
after Christianity which is the enlight
era and in India it's about before the
British came to civilize us and after
they civilized us so we have to do self
filation you know take a whip and whip
ourselves that we were backward before
the British came and they civilized and
uplifted us so we have never decolonized
the process hasn't even started we are
not a postcolonial Society we are still
deeply colonized and our governments
have done done nothing to change that so
that's why we see what you are refering
to
rodit okay Arin Shu says I am from
Bangladesh from a Sunni family I've been
suffering from religious trauma for two
years since I am 15 since I was 15 years
old my surroundings are all
superstitious people hard to explain how
disgusting it feels no one knows about
it I learned various scientific things
from the internet including psychology
which helped me to develop a rational
and hard mindset it helped me to not do
anything wrong but I don't know how long
I can hold I'm now 17 this trauma has
now created depression anxiety PTSD
anger issues in me am I the only one in
the world who suffered from this kind of
disorder that I don't match with
anyone uh m i I completely understand
what you're saying look you're not the
only one in the world who feels like a
misfit in
society you clearly
are a very intelligent
person so you are not the only person in
the world it there are others like you
so what do you do about the situation
that you find yourself in you ex you you
are born in a society that that doesn't
suit
you you have higher
standards so you can
either
um indulge in self-pity and feel sorry
for yourself and do nothing with your
life or you can take action what action
what is the objective of the action that
that you should take the objective of
the action that you need to take is that
is to remove yourself from the society
and go to a better Society
you need to go to a different country
maybe to the Western World maybe to the
United States or wherever it is that you
feel is a society that that
matches uh you and and and the standards
that you have and the aspirations that
you have for yourself where will you be
able to fit in better and where will you
be able
to develop yourself fully and rise to
the fullest extent of your potential you
have to first of all identify what
societ soy that is what country that is
and then you have to find a way of
reaching that place so one of the ways
to do that is to study hard and get very
good marks and then go to a foreign
country for higher higher education and
then get into the job market there and
settle down there and then eventually
get permanent residency or citizenship
so you have
to create a game plan for yourself that
in this much time let's say in 5 years
or whatever I'm going to go to that
place because what you're saying I
understand the kind of society that you
are currently in it is not the right
Society for you you're not happy there
you will never be happy there so you
need to remove yourself from
there so that's what I would say
uh figure out your game plan figure out
how you will reach where you want to
reach and then work at as hard as
possible as you can to achieve that
you're clearly an intelligent person
you're clearly a person with much higher
standards so it is certainly possible
for you to achieve this and to succeed
at that as long as you are disciplined
and you work hard at that so I don't
know the specific circumstances of of
your life so I can't tell you anything
beyond that I can't give you more
specific advice but I would say that
don't be discouraged don't don't give up
you clearly have some fortitude and
strength in inside yourself which uh
tells me that you'll be able to work
hard and succeed
in going to a to to a country or a
society where you fit in much better so
all the best my friend and I hope to
hear from you in the future where you
are happier and way more
successful way more successful than you
are right now and you are young you're
just 17 you have your whole life ahead
of you
so don't get discouraged be positive
think positive make your game plan and
execute work very hard and reach where
you're supposed to be where you're
destined to be all the best my friend
all the
best okay sidar sidu says why has our
civilization shifted from new inventions
and discoveries to merely following
established Paths of other countries in
fields like AI Rockets Etc why aren't we
exploring Uncharted territories like
anti-gravity military robots Iron Mine
type suit because why not Etc to gain
the first move Advantage as that can
completely change the scenario as as it
did when the US developed the world
world's first nuclear bomb you know if
you tell somebody today from somebody
from from somebody from the West for
example that India was once in the past
the world's most technologically
advanced Society they'll laugh at you
they say what the hell are you talking
about India is the a backward country
India what how can India ever have been
the most advanced country and so on
that's where we are
today through no fault of ours we were
colonized and occupied by foreign powers
for roughly a millennium roughly steady
less but whatever and they destroyed
everything that was good about our
society now we're trying to rebuild we
we are beginning the phase of starting
to rebuild so we are in the very
beginning pH
um in the past let's say during the
sarasti Sindu era the haran era we were
the world's most technologically
advanced Society by far we had the best
mathematicians scientists Brahma Gupta y
everybody so many um and even later
during the um kushan era during the
Gupta era Etc we were still the best
technologically most advanced
society and we had the best education
system in the world the University
system and all
that and that's why we were because we
had this very strong Foundation of a
very robust education system and a very
open-minded Society because of the
culture and civilization that we have
that's why we were at the Forefront of
scientific and technological
innovation that's why we were there
and geopolitically you will be at the
top only if you are technologically at
the top top otherwise you'll always be a
second R power and an occupied or
colonized power a non-sovereign power so
it is imperative for a nation that is
ambitious it's imperative for such a
such a nation to be technologically at
the Forefront of of the
world so now today why are we following
in other people's footsteps if you look
at ISRO we are doing we're trying to do
things that were done in the
1960s right
if you look at U other Industries we are
way behind we are still trying to
develop a jet engine the kind of jet
engine that was developed long ago we
are trying to follow in other nations
footsteps we're trying to develop a twin
engine aircraft fighter aircraft which
is good I'm not saying we should not do
that but everything we're do doing is
what others have already done long
ago where's the Innovation where's The
Cutting Edge research why aren't we
doing some research that nobody else has
done before
that first of all is because much much
of our defense industry is in the hands
of the government which means very
bureaucratic uh bureaucrats don't
understand science or anything they they
just want things to remain the same they
don't like change that's one reason
secondly we have an abysmally poor
education
system that doesn't teach you how to do
research it doesn't teach you how to
innovate it it discourage discourages
you from innovation it identifies people
who want to innovate and destroys
them it wants Conformity it wants
sameness it teaches you Concepts and
things that were that that should have
been taught 20 years ago it doesn't
teach you the new research that happened
in the last 20 30 years it only teaches
you old Concepts and so on so the
education system is very poor that's one
of the reasons why we are not innovating
and secondly because of the uh because
of the uh
business environment and climate that we
have that's why private companies aren't
able to uh come to the Forefront of
innovation in areas like space research
Etc like SpaceX in the US we don't have
any SpaceX in India we have a small
couple of small private companies that
are trying to do something but they have
not been treated well one of the
companies was trying to develop reusable
Rockets but they're now trying they are
now selling missile technology solid
state missile technology solid fuel
missile technology to other
countries sad State of Affairs
so the system in India prevents you from
innovating it doesn't want you to rise
too high tall poppy syndrome if somebody
Rises too high top them down to size the
government needs to change these things
the government needs to make India
competitive the government needs to
throw out the the new education policy
and completely transform the education
system completely transform it but it's
not happening so it's not going to
change for a while for a long
while um soic Arya says is I've seen all
your videos possibly on YouTube really
thank you so much thank you so much I
really appreciate that I really
do uh so I've come to realize that
things are in Cycles things ex yeah
history repeats itself in cycles and
conflict is inevitable yes how should we
prepare as young people for the future
other than what's taught to us
institutionally what are the things that
we must
do that's a very good question the only
constant in life is change things keep
changing all the time the world keeps
changing we have to keep uh we cannot be
left behind so history repeats itself in
cycles and conflict is inevitable the
the history of humankind is a history of
conflict and warfare and we've had we've
passed through a period since 1945 of
reasonable long-term peace which is
unnatural I mean there have been Wars
and all that in various parts of the
world but
for much of the world there's been a lot
of stability and peace and it's it's
been way too long actually it's been
very unnatural so you can now expect a
period of increased instability conflict
perhaps War we don't want that I never I
would never wish that for the world but
we know that that's the nature of the
world so how can young people prepare
for that first of all we have to
understand you have to understand this
that your educational degree doesn't
count for anything when your nation is
at
war or when your nation is really
striving striving to to rise fast your
educational degree counts for
nothing even as things are in the next 5
to 10 years no no body will care about
your educational
degrees in the US there are so many
companies already that don't care what a
job applicant's education degree is they
test the job applicant they test the
skills of the job applicant and even if
you have never completed high school or
whatever as long as you have the skills
required for the job they will give the
job so the first thing you to understand
is that forget about degrees acquire
skills understand what your aptitude is
maybe you're good at engineering maybe
you're good at carpentry maybe you're
good at
whatever acquire
skills you see Alexander the
Greek had
conquered he had he had conquered
territories all the way to Persia and
the border of India before he was at the
age where you get a BC or ba
degree yeah he had already that much
that that many achievements by the time
you get your bachelor's
degree right um scanda Gupta had
fought dozens of battles against the
Huns and saved India multiple times
before he was at the age where you get
your bachelor's
degree people had actual achievements in
the past by the time they were 18 today
by today in today's world by even at the
age of 25 you have no you're just
starting off now what do I do I got my
bachelor's degree master's degree maybe
MBA now what what do I do and even at
that age you don't have actual skills
you just have a degree so understand
that in the future very near future the
nation will need skills not degrees
Society will need kills India is going
to have to really buckle up and work
really hard to survive in the current
geopolitical climate and it's going to
be an increasingly uncertain
geopolitical climate and for the economy
to thrive we will need people with
skills not degrees your degrees come
from nothing if you can't do the job so
acquire skills understand yourself first
of all what am I good at what am I
really good at what am I great at and
then acquire your degrees if you want
acquire your skills along the way you
can work study for your degree and get a
degree as well but acquire skills
secondly you have to be physically fit
if the nation is at
War you have to be physically fit so you
have to be physically fit you have to
have skills degrees don't count for much
and you have to be able to learn skills
fast new
skills sometimes old skills are of no
use and you will have to learn new
skills because technology is changing
very fast so you have to learn how to
learn fast that is also a skill you'd
require so uh prepare yourself in this
manner learn how to learn learn how to
have an open mind don't have a closed
mind learn fast
don't take six months to learn SQL learn
it in 12 hours just an
example learn very fast and and execute
fast become action oriented not talk
oriented we need people of action in the
country we Indians love to talk and
argue all day so we need to transform
ourselves as a society and obviously we
need to have high standards high
standards always raise your standards so
these are the things young people need
to
do to be prepared for all
eventualities in the
coming period of geopolitical turmoil
which could last 20 50 years who knows
yeah so yeah that's what we need to
do okay let's take some more questions
from the live
chat mclen says why don't cnis have a
stayed in India because Sy lies west of
India in present day Pakistan Pakistan
occupied Sy temporarily Pakistan
occupied
sy so this the syis are an ethnic group
whose Homeland is Sy they have a state
but it's currently occupied by a
artificial temporary Nation you can't
create a new state for for them in in
what currently is India what we need is
to have syn back in India in the
National enem we we speak about Sy but
it's not in India so we need to make
that happen sooner rather than
later Grim soad says SAR reservation and
private sectors are please please please
not that we need to end reservations we
need to have only
Merit and yeah we know that there are
various uh communities and sectors of
Indian Society sections of Indian
society that
are financially backward and so on so
you can give them
um financial assistance based on their
financial con financial status Financial
cons condition you can give them free
education throughout their education uh
life
cycle that's the kind of assistance you
can give to people who are financially
backward but just because of you are
born in some Community you get
reservations for the rest of your life
what nonsense is that that is what
destroys Nations so we don't want
reservations in private sector s that is
a very bad idea very bad very bad is
very bad
idea
okay snea says is it true that if
Jerusalem falls jamu will also
fall um I'm not sure what if what the
connection is between Jerusalem and jamu
Jerusalem is in
Israel and jamu is in Northern India
what's the connection I'm not sure what
the connection is so um no if Jerusalem
falls why does jamu have to fall I don't
there's no connection as far as I can
see okay naen says will AI replace it
jobs in India what will be the future of
students who have recently joined IT
jobs um AI will replace a lot of IT jobs
for example
um you can I mean AI what chat GPT or
grock or whatever can do a lot of
programming for you you just enter the
prompt and tell them what you need to to
be done and they will write the whole
python script
or JavaScript or whatever they want
whatever you need and you can get it
done like that and you can you may need
to tweak the code a little bit or
whatever but something that would take
hours can now be done in
seconds
so the the kind of job that would take
20 people in the past you can just get
it done by one person with the help of
AI so AI will definitely you know
replace a lot of IT jobs in India so
what's the future of students who have
recently joined IT jobs they need to
resk and find something find a sector
where where AI will not be able to take
away jobs from there are so many sectors
I mean you know when you have got a
master's degree or something you aspire
to be in an office with glass windows
and you want to be in an air conditioned
room and you need you want to be at a
desk with a laptop or a computer and
that's kind of that's the kind of
comfortable job you want but those jobs
will go now so you have to be willing to
do jobs that are not as comfortable but
that will pay you
well there are lots of real world
problems out there and those problems
need Solutions which means
jobs
so so you will have to migrate to other
things maybe real real jobs which
require your hands you you to work with
your hands perhaps maybe go into road
construction I that that can pay really
well I'm not saying become a
construction laborer I'm saying become
start a construction company employ lots
of people or or you know infrastructure
building or or engineering
jobs uh
engineering we need to build ships we
need to build cranes we need to build
aircraft drones whatnot we need so many
jobs in these sector does so you know
when the IT jobs start drying out people
will have will have no option but to
either sit at home jobless or to resk
themselves and go into the sectors and
industries where AI cannot take away
jobs from so that's what students will
need to do I know it's not your Optimum
solution you want to be sitting in an AC
room in a nice glass glass walled
building sitting at a desk with a laptop
but that's not the future of the world
so
so there is a solution there are lots of
solutions and options but it's not going
to be easy you have to first of all resk
yourself and then you have to be willing
to take up a job that was not your first
choice but it's something the country
needs so the solution is ask yourself
what are the sectors in which the
country needs
jobs which are which are which which a
cannot take over and then go into that
okay um some more questions
um Nishant says is it possible for the
SAR Nations to have
a a common currency like the EU has what
could the challenges be Sark is defunct
Sark is obsolete Sark is dead Sark will
never be revived so no point why is Sark
dead because of
Pakistan an organization or grouping of
nations in which the two largest nations
can't get along together that
organization can never does not does not
have a
future in India is the top dog obviously
in the subcontinent the largest nation
and most powerful Nation by far and
India doesn't want to be the same table
as Pakistan why would we want to be at
the same table as a terrorist Nation
Sark is finished Sark is dead so India
can get I mean we have bilateral
multilateral Nation relations with all
the other nations why do we need Sark
for that so Sark is over Sark is dead we
haven't had a sark Summit in in many
years because India has refused to go
for that so it's over so what's the
point of having a common
currency uh eventually you may have a
common bricks currency or something
possibly or not we'll see about that but
a sark currency is not going to
happen okay I see question about Syria
which I've already addressed in the
beginning of the this episode so you can
watch back and take a look at what I
what I said there
um dunger Singh Chan says are Russian
scientists more advanced than Western
scientists I've readed Quantum biology
for example was there in Russia before
it came to the West Uh Russian scci
Soviet scientists used to be the some of
the best in the world in India in the
20th century in the 50s 60s ET if you
were a physicist or you were or you were
studying to be a physicist you had to
take uh lessons in basic Russian because
a lot of the literature of physics you
know the literature is in academic
research papers in physics most many of
them were written in in in Russian and
some of the best papers were written in
Russian so Russia had excellent
scientists not just in physics but in
all kinds of other fields and they had
some of the best Technologies of the
second of the of the 20th century and
even now you have excellent scientists
in Russia I'm not sure about Quantum
biology quantum ology is kind of
interesting
field yeah but yeah I'm I'm sure even
today there are sectors in industry in
engineering and even in pure Sciences
where Russians will be better than the
West for example in in pure mathematics
Russian mathematicians are some of the
best uh one example is obviously Gregor
pman right the guy who solved the Ware
conjecture and so many more so it's it's
definitely
very likely there are there are lots of
that that there are lots of Russian
scientists who are much better than
Western scientists and there there will
be research Labs Etc that are superior
to the labs that you have in the same
field or same domain in the
west
okay
um what other questions do we have live
the live chat uh Bangladesh have already
covered so I'll not take it again
[Applause]
um okay Mr 88 says what are your
thoughts on the recent emergency
declared by South Korea so just this
past week the South Korean president
declared martial
law and then had to withdraw it just a
few hours
later so what happened is that the
guy who is kind of the Donald Trump you
can you can compare him to to Donald
Trump in the US his kind of the South
Korean Donald Trump somewhat um and his
party is kind of the Maga party in in
South Korea okay so this
guy goes on TV late at night and
announces that I declaring martial
law
but he made several huge blund
blunders look when a president declares
martial law it is called a self CP an
auto coup which means he is
consolidating his power
by shutting down all political activity
and taking control of of the country
militarily so if you want to do that
here's what you have to do before you
make any announcements you have to send
the military to the Parliament building
and secure it seal it shut it down don't
let anybody enter or exit if it's late
at night nobody's inside so don't let
anybody come inside number one number
two secure all the prominent opposition
leaders I'm I'm just saying I'm not
advocating anybody do this but that's
how a coup is done where's the book I
don't know where it is it's somewhere
here Edward Dr Edward lak's book uh K uh
practical handbook so first of all you
shut down the parliament you send the
Army there make sure nobody can come
inside secondly you locate all the
prominent opposition leaders or anybody
who can be a problem for you and you
arrest them and put them in a nice five
Hotel let them chill there but you
arrest them make sure that they cannot
communicate with the public or go
anywhere put them in the house or arrest
or whatever I'm not advocating anything
harsher than that okay but in a c much
harsher things can
happen and then you take control of all
the news stations of all the news
agencies of all the newspapers of all
the big media Outlets TV stations radio
stations whatever and you take control
of each of these send your Armed Forces
there once you take full control of the
country in this manner then you go on TV
and declare martial law you don't do it
the other way around that you first
declare martial law and then you try to
secure everything how amateurish is that
so this guy the president of South Korea
he did the he did the wrong in the wrong
sequence he first went and declared
martial law but then the the all the
lawmakers they went to the Parliament
and they passed the resolution or
whatever saying that we are ending
martial
law and because of the techn of the
technicalities marshall law ended
immediately so I sit in an air CL in an
airplane I had just heard that martial
law is declared I take off on what a
five and a half hour flight when I land
I get the news my phone Marshall L is
over what a joke what an amateur that
guy
is so uh at the end of the day it has uh
achieved nothing uh I'm sure there is
much more to this than what I'm telling
you what are the geopolitical
considerations what is the US angle
because South Korea is an occupied
country it's under us occupation it's a
US proxy
State um I still haven't studied the the
deeper geopolitical uh implications of
this and where does the US stand in this
so maybe I'll look into it and we can
have the same discussion in the next
episode but as of now I can tell you
this that it was a complete blunder by
the South Korean
president so yeah good question there
yeah
uh let's take some more questions okay
let's take this question from viddi vidy
says why can't we ordinary
citizens excuse me come
together can't we ordinary citizens come
together and build an autonomous
University for ourselves where the
merit-based system is applicable with
bat's interest in the Forefront it's
possible um you need to First first of
all bring together a large number of
like-minded citizens who have the same
objective that you're putting over here
a lot of people don't have this
objective so first of all we need to
bring together a large number of
like-minded citizens then you need to
have each of them pull a certain amount
of money not a small amount of money for
this cause then you need to appoint
somebody who will who's a trustee of the
money a person who can genuinely Trust
will not embezzle the money right then
you need to have a person who's the
leader who will oversee the
the the construction I mean the the the
formation of the universe not the not
the physical con not just the physical
construction but the actual formation of
the
University what kind of University will
it will it be how large will it be what
courses will be taught what departments
will be there how will we do the hiring
what are the criteria for hiring what
kind of people do we not want as as
professors what kind of people do we
want professors so many things have to
be decided and considered and finalized
so you'll need some real high quality
leaderships not some random person who
decides I am the leader and I'll decide
this is all so you can already see how
complex it's becoming then if you have
sufficient funding you will need to
purchase land and I'm not sure what
government approvals you need to create
a private university but it's certainly
possible so you'll have to navigate the
red tape and get the approval from the
government which will need political
connections possibly I don't
know and then you have to
see um what then you have to ensure that
it gives genuine value to the
students uh I not sure whether India's
private universities need to have
reservations in case they don't then
then you can certainly do it so it is
something that uh is feasible is very
difficult first of all to raise the
funds a few hundred cres a few thousand
crores you may need to
raise not a small amount of money you
need to have the right person who will
manage the money which is again very
difficult and you need the right now of
leadership who really understands
Academia and
education that person needs to be the
overall director of the of the project
and uh yeah it's possible it's it's a
big Endeavor a difficult
Endeavor it's first of all very
difficult to get the right kind of
people together critical mass of people
overall it's possible we have 1.4
billion people we can certainly find the
right kind of people to to do this
project so it's possible but difficult
not
impossible okay let's go back to uh the
questions that we had from the
comments okay this is
by mudgal C Miss why is suffering I
think what she's trying to ask is why is
there suffering in
life that's a deep philosophical
question but a question that's relevant
to all of us why is there suffering in
life now to answer that question let's
first clarify what is suffering
suffering is is pain right the the the
sensation of pain which doesn't have to
be physical pain by banging your hand or
here something it could be psychological
pain it could be spiritual pain pain
which is non-physical generally comes
from loss when you lose
something say you're 12 years old you've
lived 12 years on the planet and
everything is nice and it's your
childhood childhood is generally happy
if you have good parents and so on so
everything is well and good you live in
your house and you go to school and you
go to the Garden to play or the park to
play and you have video games and
whatnot you have some nice friends
hopefully so it's a nice happy childhood
now the same person when you are 25
you're out of school College University
you're now working your childhood is the
thing of the past you may have moved to
a different city you no longer see your
parents regularly you've lost touch with
many of your friends because they're
also oldw workking you've experienced
some loss it gives you some sadness that
now I am I have to work now for a living
and I'm no longer able to enjoy the life
I had just a few years ago sense of loss
there now you let's say you're in your
40s you are completely disconnected with
your friends maybe you are married or
whatever maybe you have a kid or
kids at some point in time in your life
you will lose your parents that is a
shattering
loss shattering gut-wrenching horrible
the worst sensation you can have but
everybody will go through that you're
going to it's it's bound to happen you
lose that you feel a
drift the people the two people who
always took care of you who could always
rely on a
gone you feel lost that
is well that's an example of suffering
by the time you're in 50s the world has
changed the kind of movies you used to
watch no longer exist you can only see
them in archival footage today's movies
you don't understand very different
Sensibility
the music used to enjoy as a kid very
different music today the kids the
youngsters of today you can't understand
them you can't relate with relate to
them the old world you've lost maybe the
place where you grew up the home the the
neighborhood it has been redeveloped
your your home has been pulled down
bulldozed the whole neighborhood is gone
and maybe now you have apartment
complexes there you can't even recognize
the place anymore the world the physical
world of your childhood has been
bulldozed that's that's pain that's loss
now you're you're in your 60s and 70s
many of your friends have
died the people who you grew up with
they no longer
exist you then you're in your 80s almost
nothing of your childhood and of your
adult life exists anymore you have very
few people that you can connect with
mostly people of your your age so much
loss all of this is suffering change is
suffering loss is suffering that's why
life is
suffering and it's inevitable every
single person goes through this so
that's why life is suffering but it's up
to you how to deal with it it is
inevitable that every person who lives
to a certain age will go through all
these
things so does it mean that there's no
point in life and it's only pain and
suffering no it's not like that you know
it's going to go happen to you you know
everybody goes through this so you
prepared for it mentally and you still
need to
find meaning in life by doing things by
connecting with people by allying with
people by making friends by creating
things for society by creating value for
society so yes you will experience loss
over and over but you also create value
and you find meaning in creating good
things for society and providing value
to society and at the end of the day if
on your last day when the last day
comes and by the time you have provided
more value to society than you've taken
from it from society then I think you've
lived a good life so that's just the
nature of life and yeah it is suffering
you do suffer it's painful but there's a
lot of happiness and joy depending on
the choices you make and the actions
that you
undertake so you can see it two sides of
the same coin you can see it positively
you can see it negatively but it is what
it is
so the amount of pleasure and joy and
happiness or pain that you experience in
life some of it is you can't change but
a lot of it is entirely up to you and
your attitude and have you approach
life
right okay um if humans can't see
ultraviolet rays I'm sure it's UV if
humans can't see ultraviolet rays and
other Ray how did we create tools to
measure these things so there are two
kinds of invisible light infrared and
UltraViolet you know this the the
rainbow rainbow Spectrum right red Vib
gor violet indigo
green Vib blue okay Vib g y those those
colors so if we go past the red end of
the spectrum you go into infrared
territory and if you go beyond the
Violet end of the spectrum you go into
ultraviolet territory these are also
light rays but they are invisible to our
eyes we cannot detect that so how was
this discovered is the question right
how how how did we create tools to
measure or discover this so uh infrared
light was discovered in I think 1800 or
thereabouts so infrared was was was
discovered in 1800 and UltraViolet was
discovered the next year in 1801 so the
guy who discovered infrared light his
name was William hsel and he did a bunch
of experiments that which involved
sunlight so what he did was he took a
prism you know what a prism is it's this
you know the prism right it's a It's
Made of Glass so he took a glass prism
and he had a ray of sunlight fall upon
it which created a spectrum which which
split the ray of light the white light
into its component
colors and this spectrum then he
projected it on a table and over there
at every different color of light he put
thermometers there to measure the
temperature of each color of light okay
and he was able to isolate specific
Colors by by having slits and all that
so he passes the sunlight through the GL
glass prism he creates he has the
Spectrum projected on a nearby table he
has thermometers placed in each of these
different parts of the of the spectrum
Violet green red Etc and he measures the
temperature of each of these various
colors of
light and he found that the temperature
increases from The Violet end of the
spectrum towards the red of end of the
spectrum so Violet is cooler and then as
you as you go towards red it gets warmer
and warmer that's what he discovered and
then he said what if I put a thermometer
beyond the red end of the spectrum what
happens there but there is no visible
light and he found that it's even hotter
than the red light than than the red end
of the spectrum so that's how we
discovered infrared light the next year
there was another guy called Ritter
Johan Ritter who said that if this
happened let's do it the other way
around okay so I think it was a German
he did it the next year so what he did
was he did a series of experiments not
with thermometers but with silver
chloride silver chloride is a chemical
that darkens when it's exposed to to
light not to sunlight but to any kind of
light so uh what he did is that he also
used a glass prism to to split the
spectrum of sunlight and he placed
silver chloride in different parts of
the spectrum and he noticed that it
became it it darkened more quickly
towards the Violet end of the spectrum
and then he took the silver chloride and
he put it Beyond The Violet end of the
spectrum and then he saw that it it
became even darker okay so even though
there is no visible light there it
became even darker it was an even more
intense
reaction in the invisible part of the
spectrum Beyond Violet and that's how
ultraviolet light was discovered so
that's how in the very beginning of the
19th century infrared as well as
ultraviolet light was discovered through
this scientific
methodology
okay Vikram geopolitical says your views
on masterpiece is like Interstellar not
getting a single screen in India and
Third Rate Cinema like pushpa 2 getting
all the attention when will the Indian
audience be served with good cinema okay
I have I have no I I have no idea what
pushpa 2 is I have not seen it I have
not even heard of it until now I don't
watch all these movies I love cinema by
the way I like good movies so I don't
watch any of these Indian movies because
most of them are I don't like
them
uh so when will Indians will when will
the Indian audience be served with good
cinema the Indian audience will be
served with good cinema when the
majority of people like good
cinema you are getting what you like
it's not about me I like better Cinema
than the rest of the Indian audience
it's about the average preference it's
about the preference of the average
Indian person the average Indian person
the majority of the Indian people prefer
things like whatever you're talking
about push Patu or or whatever is is
whatever comes on the o platforms and
all that I can't stand those things but
that's what most Indians like now if I
can't stand it it's my problem right
most Indians love it so they get to
watch it and more and more such content
is created so the market seems to be
Democratic more or less what people like
they're given that because that makes
the most money for the
producers um I certainly was looking
forward to watching intersell again I
think it was released many years ago
about roughly a decade or so ago roughly
roughly
2014 2016 somewhere around that I
watched it on the big screen it's one of
the best movies I've seen in my entire
life loved it not just the physics part
and the science part of it but also the
overall story it was great wonderful and
when I heard that it's going to be
re-released this year I thought let me
go and watch it again and I would have
given good money to watch it again on
the on the big screen but not a single
screen in India showed the
movie very disappointing and I can't
just go to another country just to watch
a movie right I mean I can't justify
that
expense go to what Singapore or Hong
Kong to watch a movie and come back
imagine that so yeah I won't be able to
watch it very very disappointing but the
Indian audience love certain kind of
content entertainment content and that's
why they get
it um so hopefully in the future we our
our audience our people will develop
better taste in cinema and entertainment
hopefully in the future
okay let's take a couple more questions
from the live
chat um Kos of the game says what does a
probability density function how does it
work can you please explain
it okay you're talking about s s right
the wave function so the wave function
is a complex function it has the
imaginary component which has
I and it denotes the probability of
finding a particle in a certain point in
space not space time space in quantum
mechanics we don't do time in quantum
mechanics time is a classical uh
parameter an external parameter a
classical parameter uh so um the
probability function s it tells you what
is the probability of finding a certain
particle at a specific point in space
threedimensional two dimensional space
let's do three dimensionally right so
that's what it tells you uh so it's it
it so you it Maps the probability space
the the probability in across space of
finding the particle now how does it
work the part the the the wave function
Itself by itself doesn't tell you
anything but when you normalize the the
wave function when you take the when you
normalize it that's when it actually
gives you the the pro the probability of
finding the particle U so I cannot
explain it Beyond this without resorting
to
equations but what I can tell you is
that it it gives you the probability of
finding the particle at a at a specific
point in
space so it's it's a fuzzy thing okay if
you look at the orbitals of let's say
the hydrogen atom then you get these
shapes okay depending on the
configuration of on what state the atom
is in whether it's the ground state the
first excited state of whichever State
okay and you get different shapes of the
orbital so these orbital shapes come
from the wave function which is a
probability density
function and of course we have the
observer effect in which the entire
thing collapses to a point because of an
observation which is a different story
so that's what I can tell you in brief
without going into diagrams or
equations okay
um sarange says do you believe in
celibacy celibacy it's a hated argument
nowadays please reply look celibacy is
not for
everybody most humans want to not be
celbrate most of whether you want to
procreate or just enjoy the pleasure of
not being celbrate it's not for most
people it's only for very few people
with who want to achieve great things
and who have great willpower like goam
Buddha or whatever um I
don't beyond that I don't know what to
say okay I don't think it's for
everybody it's for very few people it is
said that if you remain celibate for a
certain amount of time then your
willpower everything increases improves
all that well um I am no expert in that
so I'll rather not comment about that uh
yeah I'm no expert in this
matter John V says what's your take on
Donald Trump's recent tweets on bricks
and Bricks currency and dollarization uh
bricks Nations yeah so Trump recently
tweeted that uh if the brics Nations try
to create a brics currency and and move
away from the US dollar then he's going
to destroy them he's going to impose
100% tariffs on Imports coming from
those Nations which will make the US
market impossible to enter for these
nations that's thing so he has
essentially thrown down the gauntlet and
given an ultimatum to Bricks that if you
even think of dollariz I'm going to
destroy your economies now how feasible
is this um the US needs a lot of Chinese
products right a lot of the stuff that
is sold in the US products that are sold
in the US are manufactured in China so
all of that is being imported by the US
from China and these are things the US
market
needs now if you put a 100% tariff on
that then the prices will double
overnight is that not going to crush the
US economy as
well so a lot of what Donald Trump says
is hyperbowl
hyperbole he exaggerates a lot but he
can certainly do that to Nations like
India from which the India doesn't
export anything comparable to the
volumes that China exports to the US and
if Indian manufactured products are
taxed at 100% And they became become
twice as expensive it won't hit the US
market that badly so maybe he can do it
to Nations like India smaller economies
like India but definitely not to China
so I think he's
simply uh trying to bully look Trump has
that personality he will try to bully
you so he's try to bully the bricks
Nations it can work with some Nations
but it will be counterproductive if if
applied to Nations like
China all right let's take maybe one
more question
um uh what do we have uh let's see let's
see let's see om beer says will the fall
of Bashar al- Assad's regime in Syria
affect India's interests in our media
look
uh
the terrorist outfit whatever you want
to call it that has taken over uh Syria
is a Turkish and American
proxy so this significantly
strengthens
turkey's uh geopolitical stance in the
region power projection abilities it uh
is is is great for erdogan and if Turkey
feels stronger and bolder then it also
helps aeran because aeran you can say is
a Turkish proxy turkey aeran are like by
okay turky
brothers and
aeran is armenia's mortal enemy which
and so is turkey and turkey and aeran
want to wipe Armenia essentially off the
map of the world and create a pan tury
panan Corridor so if you look at all of
these connections then the fall of
Bashar al- Assad's regime in Syria
greatly strengthens turkey in the region
which will obviously have a positive
effect on azaran and combined together
it will be bad for Armenia and make
Armenia feel even even more
insecure and we have interest in Armenia
Russia has interest in Armenia and India
and Russia are kind of working together
in a some ways in Armenia so it can
certainly affect India's interest in
Armenia very interesting question that
you asked because it it involves all
those connections all right we are done
with today's live stream lots of
questions have taken thank thank you so
much for all the really interesting
questions you ask especially in the
comments and even in the live stream
live chat I really appreciate that so
I'm going to end this live stream over
here take care all of you keep asking
questions keep raising your standards
and I will see you definitely in next
next weekend in next weekend in the next
live stream thank you and I'll see you
soon bye-bye